This is Wyatt from Castle Island. And today on the podcast, I was joined by Alex Lynn,
founding partner of Reforge. Having launched earlier this year, Reforge is a venture capital firm
focused on investing in the next generation of blockchain and deep tech infrastructure.
And without further ado, I hope you enjoy my conversation with Alex.
As a specific inducement to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy,
but only as an expression of their personal opinion. This podcast is for informational purposes only.
75 billion pounds more to Britain's ailing economy with a new round of quantitative easing.
And print a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry. So out of this
worry, we have something called the Bitcoin. Bitcoin. Alex, thanks for joining me. I've been
excited to have you on the pod for a while. I think it would probably be great to start with
a personal introduction. So would love to hear more about you and what you're up to these days
and your road in crypto. First of all, thanks for having me on huge fan of the podcast.
I think we can kind of go back to college. I went to the Virginia Military Institute and
for a long time on the website, the banner would say, don't do ordinary,
which encapsulated a lot of my experience there. You're going to a school that requires you to
dress up in a uniform requires you to go through intense, rigorous physical training.
But then at the end of it all, you might not commission in the military.
A lot of people have asked me over time, why did you go to VMI if you didn't commission as an officer?
And I think it just kind of brings about this idea of don't do ordinary in my life.
It's just been a common theme, which I can allude to in many different examples.
But this is also relevant because I got into crypto during my time at VMI. So I
made my first Bitcoin, not through mining. So this is 2012, but through a little online business
that I created through RuneScape Bot Farming. And those listeners that aren't familiar, RuneScape
is a very popular MMORPG game that is very rigorous and intense in and of itself when it comes to
grinding out stats, making golds kind of like a virtual medieval Sims in a way. And so I found a
way to automate the playtime. And it was very lucrative. Gold mining and selling gold for
real world cash is very popular among MMORPGs like RuneScape and World of Warcraft. And I had
some buyers that were interested in buying my accounts using Bitcoin because the foreign
exchange rate on PayPal was 4.5%. So that was my first foray into Bitcoin. And that kind of
started the whole idea of don't do ordinary in a more professional sense. So then graduated,
went into consulting for a little bit, tried to join the blockchain group at Deloitte. And at the
time they were focused on hyperledger implementation. So private blockchains really promoted by IBM.
And a lot of the consulting firms were very on top of it back then.
When was this?
This was 2015 at this time. And fortunately, I couldn't make the transfer of classic corporate
America bureaucracy than large corporate America. But that was kind of my catalyst to
deciding to leave Deloitte and pursue the entrepreneurial spirit that I've always had
with wanting to be a part of something that I could drive impact at. So join an ad tech startup
in New York. And that was kind of my foray into startups, entrepreneurship, and being an operator.
So I was an engineer, and then eventual product manager at several web two companies,
tried my hand at starting my own company called tether health, digital healthcare company.
Throughout this process, you can kind of see the theme of don't do ordinary. I'm going to kind of
challenge myself, go against the grain, instead of taking your traditional consulting path or
your investment banking path, and being in New York for startups versus SV. And it was around
the time around 2019 that I decided, Hey, crypto is been in my life personally for a long time. And
so how do I get into it professionally? DeFi summer comes around in 2020. At this point,
I decided to go back to grad school. So I wanted to do two things with my career. At this point,
it was first, go to grad school to really differentiate myself to enter the industry.
And then to become an investor after years of being an operator. And the first was important
because I think that entering the industry as an investor, I didn't need to go to grad school.
But what I did was I really focused on understanding the primitives better than anyone
else on the investing side or wanting to, I did this technical MBA at Cornell, where I focused
on computer engineering, distributed systems, cryptography, and that set the tone for
my investing career, taking my operator experience, taking this more academic,
rigor and fundamentals approach to ensuring that, Hey, as we kind of embark on the investing
journey within this more frontier industry, that I have a very strong foundation and understanding
to what drives it all. So that landed me at Shima Capital, early stage fund generalists that focused
on all things crypto, where I was the head of research and one of the first investment team
hires. And once again, very non traditional way I was tweeting my way through Twitter, writing
research reports, reaching out to funds, sharing deals, getting my foot in the door, just based
off of the things that I was interested in writing about, caught the attention of our good friend,
Eda at Shima and started investing at Shima. And so through that process decided, Hey, I really
wanted to focus on more don't do ordinary ideas and believe that there are particular areas that
I wanted to really focus on alongside my partner now, which brings me to where I am today, which is
recently launched reforge and early stage blockchain and frontier tech investment firm
that I'm super excited to have launched to support the best founders in very unique areas that I
believe to really drive impact and move the needle within the space. Yeah, really excited for you
guys in the launch, first off needless to say, this might be a loaded question, but I'd love for
you to explain in your view, what are blockchain primitives? Blockchain primitives really goes back
to the foundations of math, mathematics, computer science, economics and philosophy. That's why it's
so interesting to me. If I were to kind of highlight my degree specifically, a lot of it
revolved around understanding consensus, understanding distributed systems, understanding
operating systems, understanding how we've kind of gone through the earliest designs of the internet
to existing internet protocols to now web three, as we know it, and what makes up web three. It's a
very broad category. And so the degree specifically focused a lot on the mathematics and the computer
science behind blockchain networks and distributed ledger technologies. But there's just so much
more to that. There's the economic component that makes up the primitives of incentives and
the Byzantine fault tolerant problem that kind of makes up the earliest forms of consensus to
ensure alignment between multiple parties and doing so through a monetary incentive,
i.e. Bitcoin, on the proof of work side. And then once we shifted over to the new consensus
designs, you still have that monetary component that's very relevant. And then persisting on,
you start to see the cyberpunk movement surface, which is the core philosophies as to why Satoshi
created Bitcoin and the whole idea of removing intermediaries. So the philosophical piece comes
in as to what motivates us, the morals and ethics of us with greed, and how that impacts us, I think,
all plays into this due to this game theory that exists within our free market economy of, hey,
do we do X to want to achieve Y when we're introduced to Z factors? That's the philosophical
piece and really understanding what drives humans and wanting us to either become irrational or
remain rational is what makes this all crazier than it already is. So it's been a loaded question,
loaded answer there as well. More of an abstract answer, I guess. It's really difficult to kind of
pinpoint, but if I were to give you something more tangible, it's a lot of the mathematics and
computer science elements of what makes up a blockchain and what is feasible and what's not
feasible to the actual underlying infrastructure. Where do you guys see innovation as being possible
within that stack of primitives or call it the existing stack of what runs blockchains?
A simplistic way to put it would be you have the execution layer, the way the transactions are
settled, you have consensus, like you mentioned, and you can obviously go deeper down to the physical
hardware that are underlying blockchain technology and other associated technologies.
Maybe if you could orient, where can we expect to see innovation within that and what's the end that
you see? I think innovation happens at all points of the stack. Starting with hardware,
there are a lot of layer one designs that will be impacted by the type of hardware you use
on the validator side. You have the execution and settlement that arguably can be improved a lot.
Solana and their movement of increased bandwidth, reduced latency has persisted within the market.
Because I think that every part of the stack can be innovated upon, I think that there are just a
lot of core assumptions that might either be flawed or should be revisited in that stack.
So one example is the virtual machine. And I think that we've seen a lot of innovation surface in the
last 12 to 18 months with respect to, hey, is the Ethereum virtual machine the most optimal
form factor for smart contract execution? You have the SVM surface and you have projects that
believe, hey, we believe the SVM is better. The slot of virtual machine is better, but we want to
tap into the EVM liquidity. And so you have projects like Eclipse come into the fold. You have
projects like movement, or you have Aptos and sweet native move L ones that say, hey, the move
language will provide a better virtual machine because of the EVM flaws. On the VM side, there's
innovation. We're going to see execution innovation. We're going to see settlement innovation. The
DA Celestia introduced a different approach to the availability. That's how modular surfaced,
but we have to be very careful with this. Because even though there's innovation opportunity at each
stack or layer, it doesn't necessarily mean you need to create a new protocol or a new company
to address those problems. We've started to see this idea or this issue where
user experience is so bad when it comes to crypto and blockchains.
Why is that, though? That's not necessarily because of the infrastructure problems. I would
pause it. I think that's for a lot of reasons. In its current state, if we specifically highlight
the modular thesis, we can say that the user experience has gotten so poorly. Let's look at
rollups. Sharding and dank sharding was a massive technical barrier that the Ethereum Foundation
and researchers decided to say, hey, I think rollups will be a better alternative solution.
And now you have many rollups in L2s that now come in and say, hey, we will help Ethereum scale.
And then because rollups now are introduced, we need DA for those rollups. We need ZKs.
So you're saying infrastructure innovation begets needs.
Correct. People just keep building things on top to improve. And you create a new market for such
tools. But I would argue that that has given us a lot of misdirection over the last several years.
But to revert back to your point, I think there's innovation to be had on every part of the stack.
And I think that's what we're really excited about.
And do you think we'll eventually get to a fast-performance blockchain that can be a
universal type of settlement layer? Or will we be multi-chain?
Our thesis is there will be an oligopoly of L1s that really promote this idea of a modular TCPIP,
where you don't really know what chain that you're building an app on. You don't really care as a user
what access point. If I need to use my MetaMask or Rabi to enter the EVM, it doesn't matter. I should
have wallets that can provide access to liquidity on any chain in this modular TCPIP underlying
network. And that's that completely abstracted away. And when you guys are looking at the areas where
you invest, which ultimately improves the efficiency and usefulness of chains, is that with primarily
financial use cases as the endpoint in mind for you? Or are you thinking about other implementations
at scale that people might not be as aware of? Definitely financial. I think financial applications
are our number one use case. Everything from stablecoins to payments to DeFi itself is a great
use case. And what DeFi has created across meme coins, lending, borrowing, perps, those goes on.
But by no means is it confined to that. I just think that we've been able to
identify a really great use case. And when we're double downing, triple downing on that.
But it goes well beyond financial applications. I think something that we're really interested in
is consumer in general. It could be anything social, it could be interest media. So this idea
where attention, it's not just social media, it's all about attention and how do you capture the
interest of society and many other social contracts that come from the benefits of
composability and coordination that blockchains offer? How do we understand that space? And
it's very difficult right now to know exactly what consumer product I want to be investing in,
because you don't really know what you don't know. If a founder or a really strong founding team
presents an idea, I'm willing to bet that there's a high probability they will pivot.
On the consumer side? Yes. So virtuals, the AI agent protocol on Ethereum,
or I guess specifically base, they used to be GameDow, building another consumer product.
Pump.fun used to be the team that was focused on NFTs. Caviar, that was not too long ago. One of
the areas that I'm most excited about is, hey, I want to invest in founding teams that are highly
experimental, that are willing to iterate. They could have no idea what they want to build.
12 months ago, Blast launched, let's capitalize and let's use this sandbox to identify and
experiment what we can do from incentives, from unique coordination mechanisms, NFTs, what have
you. And then you have another network launch in six months. And hey, I'm not promoting,
let's produce, but I think it's very important to experiment. Right now, when everything is
moving so quickly, switching costs are incredibly low for the end user. We must understand, hey,
what works in this new paradigm and what doesn't. And the only way to do that effectively is to take
bets on really, really experienced founders and founders that are willing to take risks
to experiment. That's really the only way for us to kind of do this at scale properly.
And the areas where you're seeing innovation in the consumer space,
what's material there? Or what moves the needle in terms of something that could be useful, widely
used for society will be around in 10 years. I think virtual's protocol is cool for the sake of
anyone listening. It's, to my knowledge, essentially you can buy tokens representative of these AI
agents that exist across media platforms. I see that as somewhat temporary and novel.
Go for it to push back on that front. But where do you see staying power is another way to ask that.
That's the biggest question, sustainability. That's really hard to answer today. If I knew,
then I would be investing in it and I would be shilling at this one in time. If we were to really
look at the benefits of crypto, I'd be the first to tell you, hey, we don't need a token for
everything that we're building for. And so when I think about alternatives to DeFi and then
thinking about what's sticky, crypto has this incredible ability to encode and automatically
enforce really complex social relationships and agreements. I'm only looking at consumer and maybe
we could categorize deep and decentralized physical infrastructure networks within consumer
because of the form factor of being able to interact with one. But I'm more so thinking of
true application consumer that solves a problem that I experienced day to day. If crypto is able
to enforce these complex social relationships and agreements that were previously impossible to
formalize, those problems are the ones that I think crypto is really fit to solve. So examples would be
reputation systems that can't be gamed or centrally controlled. And so I think we have the
earliest versions of that and dows and governance mechanisms that I think can always be improved
upon. That's because of the accountability of blockchains is the unlock there. The accountability
and incentives and then also composability, being able to then add on to core pillars of say a use
case and then improving it from say a different third party that is not biased or is not centrally
managed by that original core pillar or problem. Then you also have your typical, hey,
what are some coordination mechanisms for large groups of people, large entities, large agents
that doesn't have a trusted central intermediary? You have commitment devices being able to commit to
certain contracts, whether it's social, financial, legal, that are truly binding.
You know Dunbar's number, so the number of people that we as individuals can probably manage
in our day to day lives. What if there are ways to enable trust relationships that can scale
beyond Dunbar's number and doing so in a way that is both economical and technically feasible?
Once again, we have good understanding from a high level what can be enabled, but I think
execution is everything. And we just haven't seen that yet. And that's why I think from an experiment
highly iterative approach, we will be able to get closer to that outcome.
I really like this framework you've given of blockchains as enabling contracts and social
being a primary use case there. At risk of wildly generalizing a lot of businesses in the world,
a lot of the largest businesses that we see take Uber, Facebook, advertising like you mentioned,
rely on the value proposition within their closed loop systems. And if you open that up,
they will lose a lot of frankly why you use and pay for those platforms. An example being Uber
relies on a closed network where they maintain the relationships between you and the drivers.
If you open that up, they lose their value proposition. Facebook relies on being
the key holder of your network. And if you could port that elsewhere, they lose their value proposition.
Given those are the largest companies in society, do you think that
contracts, let's say social contracts enabled by blockchains have the actual potential ability to
get around that and be adopted at scale if arguably the strongest forces are going to be,
in my view, probably very opposed to that?
My immediate thought is individual empowerment is an incredibly powerful mechanism in society,
meaning how do you promote agency? And I think that that's kind of the core question I ask
of why does this all matter? Because you can say if you remove Uber as a centralized entity and
you as an individual open up an app, that allows you to connect peer to peer to drivers. And that
app is a protocol that is fully decentralized and not managed by an organization, then the
transaction occurs between you and the driver. So you're empowering the driver to manage his or her
own book of business when it comes to driving. And then on the demand side, you have
writers who want to take advantage of the service for whatever purpose. And so the barrier is the
experience we as individuals should live that way. And I think this is a little history lesson
this goes all the way back to Athenian democracy of Hey, how do you promote individual views and
perspectives within the governing body? And then you have the Renaissance, then you have the
Enlightenment, then you have the Industrial Revolution, then you have so many of these
movements in history, the civil rights to then women's rights and suffrage movements. And then
now we've entered the digital world, we've reverted back and said, Hey, you no longer have these
individual rights, because you have governing bodies within the digital realm that control you.
And so essentially, we're saying, Hey, like, how do we revert back to what has worked really,
really well for us in the physical world throughout history, but in the digital world.
And so if you're able to unlock that, because the internet itself and what it enables is a
beautiful thing makes it incredibly efficient and has created billions and billions and
trillions upon trillions of wealth for us and innovation and technology. And I think that
that increases exponentially once we focus on individual empowerment again, that transition
is only blocked by user experience. Yeah, but purely experience and the technology
infrastructure that will enable that to happen seamlessly. That is a big part of the categories
of reforge. I mean, it's in the name of the firm as to what it is that we are reforging.
We're fundamentally reforging human interaction digitally because of an improved internet and
an improved financial system. I take the stance that the platforms that thrive based off of
the signal or power of a smaller number of individuals, Twitter being one that comes to
mind are easier to disintermediate versus those that derive value from having just
a really deep, robust network. Uber being one that comes to mind in that sense,
because if you can move the high signal individuals, the people that make a Twitter
place that you want to be, I think you can create a rival platform or whatever a next generation
would be. I do think it's very difficult to move platforms that derive their value from
a collective participation that they've built over a period of many years.
I agree. I think that's why Blue Sky and a lot of the social
networks have had a difficult time pushing for adoption and proper distribution.
In a funny way, I think that the amount that we're,
some would say, chronically online promotes individualism, which probably in a way benefits
new types of social media because people are tending to gravitate towards where the individuals
they want to see are. I think TikTok is the living, breathing embodiment of that. Whereas,
I don't know about you, when I used Facebook in high school, it was all about just connecting
with their friends. You weren't following celebrities or anything like that. I feel
like it's changed a lot. I think that there is the component of monetization
and having access to content that you wouldn't have with just your friends.
If you could watch an Uncle Drew video and you don't have any friends
or basketball players, then of course you're going to want access to that. I think
the revolution of content has been fascinating.
So this is something that came up in one of our conversations today. I'm curious to hear your
respective on it. But I think a major unlock here from what blockchains can bring to social
platforms is you can arguably get unfiltered or semi-permissionless forms of social interaction
online when you have a governing body like Twitter or X, where yes, it's a centralized
governing body, but they're not going to stop you from doing essentially anything.
The harder part is, I think, our financial system is very stiff in terms of what you're
able to do online. An example of that has been the debanking issue that you've had with the
cannabis and the crypto industries, and you'll have payment service providers who don't necessarily
want to work with certain legal activities, especially where there might be more of an
element of forms of identity that are non-traditional. Crypto and blockchains can be used to be the
financial rail of what is otherwise a fairly permissionless platform and allow for a sort of
open commerce experience. In a way that has hopefully evolved what we were 10 years ago,
where you had this use behind illicit transactions, that there's a happy medium
where you have filtering in terms of making sure that there's no illicit activity and
movement to bad actors, but you allow for an open commerce experience buying and selling
that happens in a social realm. And I think if you look at the Web2 stack, they have shortcomings
that could be easily mitigated with Web3 from data modes. What's an example of that?
Data modes from these companies that have potential to hurt users is mitigated by
composability of blockchain networks and smart contracts. Can you explain that further?
This is very top of mind, especially with the recent OFAC ruling with respect to tornado cash
not being responsible for illicit activities because tornado cash was wrongly accused of
promoting illicit activity. OFAC said, hey, we don't really have the evidence
or the positioning to say that this was promoted by you guys, tornado cash.
I think privacy is surfacing again as a really important component. And this is relevant because
Bitcoin's original vision was before chain analysis and before a lot of the existing companies,
privacy was part of the cypherpunk manifesto and the whole idea is that you really couldn't
determine who was sending Bob by Bitcoin. And that was really the core ethos. When you have this
opportunity to still have an open network associated to data availability, but then doing so in a
private manner, wanting things to be secret versus wanting things to be private is very different.
Privacy still enables a data mode within products. Whereas if you look at today in Web2,
the data modes that now protect institutions no longer protect the user, you essentially switch
that with crypto, with blockchains, where you're protecting the user and the opportunity to say,
hey, me as a user, I want my data to be open on my own accord to benefit me. But then if it
doesn't benefit me and benefits others and I don't want it to be available, that should always be in
the decision of the user. And so I think that crypto switches that paradigm and makes it more
powerful for us. So that's where the agency returns back to the user.
And to put a bow on a lot of the things we've hit on, do you think the industry is
moving in the right direction in terms of implementing these sorts of new solutions you'd
like to see? I think we are. I think we're at a very important inflection point with what it is
that we're one, allocating capital towards and two, what founders want to be building with this
pool. I think we're very far from it being consensus that we're going in the right direction.
And I say that because you'll still have bad actors, you'll still have a lot of projects,
founders, investors seeking short-termism outcomes that don't really move the needle.
But I think that we're starting to shift both from regulatory clarity to better technologies,
to better incentives, to a general understanding of what it is that we're capable of building
slowly, but surely we're going to have that shift come sooner rather than later.
And what are you excited about in the next year broadly?
I'm really excited to see the changes in administration, the latest developments in
the macroeconomic environment will start to drive better human capital into this industry.
I think that human capital is probably one of the most important drivers of innovation,
if not the most important driver. And I think that's rather obvious, but I think we forget,
especially when for a long time crypto had a lot of brilliant people come in and want to
build and experiment new things, but a lot of that's dissipated with AI and a lot of other
very interesting industries. But I think because of the existing overlap that we're now seeing between
free market economic opportunity that crypto offers with enabling technologies like AI,
or edge compute, or other kind of physical infrastructure improvements, then we're going
to see an influx of individuals who are going to really look at these problems that we're
experiencing and saying, hey, I want to break the status quo and solve them. And I'm not doing it
just for the opportunity to generate wealth for myself, but because this is way bigger than
me as an individual. Cool. I love the human capital piece.
Well, Alex, thanks for coming on. I've really enjoyed chatting and excited for what's ahead
for Reforged. So appreciate you joining us. Thank you. It was a pleasure to be on.
Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island. To find out
more about Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc. To listen to all of our podcast episodes,
please go to onthebrink-podcast.com or just click on the tab in our website. Thanks for listening.